[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness, mind and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you define consciousness?
[SPEAKER_01]: In the simplest possible but accurate terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, kind of what it means for me is the fact that
[SPEAKER_00]: There are things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I tend to see it like... like, eh... there's something rather than nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm kind of alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's something... does it mean the objects that are around you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh... anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, where's the consciousness?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the consciousness in regard to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sort of negative in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the... and it can only be...
[SPEAKER_00]: I sort of think of it as just the fact that I'm alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if there weren't... if there was nothing to be discerned, there'd be no consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because there are things to be discerned, it's consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can only see consciousness through the things that are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your first, if your first point of relationship with consciousness is the fact that you're alive, does that change?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that sort of give rise to something else in its own place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Some other more specific consciousness or something like that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you mean, so, okay, so, yeah, then you could, you could then
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the fact that you're alive, you can then look at... you can then discern that things appear in different ways or in different places, different domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of that is then on account of you being alive, on account of you being conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... so, how would you then describe that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: The level of being alive?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The level of... that's what I said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just the fact that there are things, rather than...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's given.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... it's not something you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is quite different to the idea of... the common idea of what consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I am conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is in my mind, in my... in my brain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, and the scientists even, you know, try to find a center for consciousness in the brain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, it's this thing of my awareness or whatever else that comes with that, with the same characteristics of being alive, being present, being discerning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's within this body, within this, within my head, within my mind, or whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all of that within, internally, externally, internally and externally, is only distinguished on the basis of you being alive in the first place, and that's already what consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what we would refer to this conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is already there, conscious, nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fact the body is there, means consciousness is there with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have the body and then the consciousness discern later.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's more accurate... inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more accurate to say that the consciousness is out there with the things that you're conscious of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The things you're conscious of can only be done on the basis of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the most accurate thing to say is this conscious body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's with the body, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what's left for an arahant, as Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: This conscious body and everything else that kind of appears within that external to him, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not like it's something to be found in the body or...
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or separate from the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot address, or attend to, or look at your consciousness independent of the experience as a whole, as in of the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But where, basically, if there's a body there, there's consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there's consciousness there, there's a body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't help it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... it's really... the problem with consciousness is that it's... it's... it's something people overthink.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which already, you know, comes from the assumptions that you have about, like, me internally, external world, opposite of that, our consciousness is on this end, and...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look... well, any of that, any of those such distinctions or discriminations, so to speak, are possible only because you're alive in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being alive means having body that is alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is a conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Body with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Body bereft of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which I didn't ask for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: The division of you internally, and your mind internally, and the world externally, and the sense objects externally, is not the division of the body and the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a division that's within the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you look internally, the conscious body is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you look externally, the conscious body is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you look both, neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: The conscious body has to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If anything is there, there's a conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if the most abstract thought or when people say, I had this out-of-the-body experience, on account of your conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not really out-of-the-body experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out-of-the-body experience is, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: What would out of the... like, factually, out of the body experience be?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have any experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, parinibbāna, I guess, would be out of the body experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, when you're not just dead, but you're an arahant beforehand, and then the body disintegrates, and then there will be... but that wouldn't constitute an experience anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you wouldn't be out of the body experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of the body experience,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any experience known to you, even in the utter... like, utmost fantasy and abstraction, is on account of the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, saying the experience out of the body, means experience independent of the body, and that's impossible to experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you don't discern the body, which is most of the time, most... for most people, most... in most cases, you have an experience and you're not aware of the body as you're having that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that does...
[SPEAKER_00]: But doesn't change the fact...
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't change the fact the body is there and you can be aware of it because it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you could
[SPEAKER_01]: Develop that knowledge at any given time, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is kind of a task.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If...
[SPEAKER_01]: If... For somebody who is not aware that the body is there, and they kind of don't even think about it, and develop the sense of independence, or their point of view, or consciousness, or whatever else... Well, just ask yourself, would my thoughts, that are completely divorced from the body, pay no attention to the body, even think the body is second, could those thoughts remain, if I get killed next second, next moment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you ignore that necessary
[SPEAKER_01]: The fundamental dependence of anything mental on account of the physical.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's also everything is in the body, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is the ultimate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's already a mental notion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you look at the mental, it will be undermined by physical.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look at the physical, it's undermined by the mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, consciousness means, then, having a body that is alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you then, again, in simple terms, but accurate terms, define the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things are always significant, things are always meaningful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm always in a kind of situation, which I can describe in terms of my mood, or just how I understand what's going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everything, anything I attend to is always within a context of other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always within a mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's one mood, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You always have to have a mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: You always have to have a mood, but also just the fact that things are understood in relation to other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, so that just that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is within a mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is within a mood, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your interaction with things is always within the mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot be outside of the mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you pay...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same principle, even if you pay no attention to the mood... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...the order still remains there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I wouldn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: But I wouldn't say...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm in a mood and that's one way in which I can... the mind can be known.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind is that more general... Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...capacity or like a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would the relationship be between the mood and the conscious body?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the relationship?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they're both given.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're both...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm subjected to both of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're both simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: But between them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe...
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess the body sort of comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you think that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I think that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, partly because the satipaṭṭhāna's body comes first, but also
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the mood's primary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I, you know, I used to think...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, you know, the standard way of thinking is that you notice yourself in a mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not answering your question.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm kind of just going off on my own.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's all right.
[SPEAKER_00]: You notice you're in a mood, and then you think, oh, that's probably because of... let's say I'm... let's say I'm feeling agitated or something, and then you go... and you notice, oh, I've got... because I'm thinking about all these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll stop thinking
[SPEAKER_00]: changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, I'll be able to... that agitation will go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, of course, that's the wrong way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: That all those thoughts that I'm... are because of the agitation... are recognized because of the agitation.
[SPEAKER_00]: The agitation comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, therefore, there's nothing I can do
[SPEAKER_00]: To get rid of that agitation, because everything I can do is get... is part of... within this mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... so... it's the same... that's the same sort of structure as the body, in that it's like a container for a long...
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're asking what's the relationship between those two, between the conscious body and the mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: You describe the relation between the mood and the thoughts, which would have been my next question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in consciousness, mind, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of all these... all...
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts are always within a mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mood is always within a body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that the mood comes first, but that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practically, for a mind that's not freed from ignorance, what comes first is the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within thoughts, you get to discern the mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you don't abandon the lack of understanding in regard to the nature of the right order, you would then still think the thoughts come first and then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Blame them for your moods and for everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to go against the stream.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your thoughts come first, practically speaking, because that's where ignorance has taken you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: But within that, you discern the mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, you discern the mood secondary to the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you blame the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You try to stop thinking thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a lot of meditation techniques, they will prevent you from thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't get into a bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you were pointed rightly, you get to understand that thoughts and simultaneously present mood, it's actually the mood comes first, structurally, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're there at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the mood is more general.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mood is more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, there's nothing I can do in regard to these thoughts that will get below that mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: That mood... Or step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you do, it's going to be rooted in that mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any manipulation I do on those thoughts is all within that mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what we've been talking about so extensively.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the things you can attend to, things you can think about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the peripheral in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you discern peripheral as secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you realize, no, peripheral is the container, the primary container.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you get to get the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was just going to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You discern the sign of the mind in regard to your thoughts, in regard to, like, actual present experience that you attend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's such a wrong view to think you can attend to your mind in the same sense you attend to other objects, including thoughts, because thoughts are mental objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Objects of the mental sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: That I can attend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the sights are objects of the visual sense
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's thought... many thoughts going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some thoughts are peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are peripheral thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... but the mind is something... is that thing that's the sort of background of those thoughts that I cannot attend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... as I said, you start... you have to start first with thoughts, then discern the mind rightly, in the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is that which is the first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts are secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any movement of my thought in regard to my mood is within the mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's discernment of the mood that will free you from the mood, not the particular set of movements of your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can go further, following the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you get established in that notion of your own mind, that peripheral sign, that peripheral container of what the mood is, you also then get to see what's peripheral to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can I just... What is a necessary basis for having any mood in the other day, regardless of the thoughts that might be moving within it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Conscious body, having a body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having a beating heart or operating body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize that is the peripheral container to your mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you can't get underneath that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't disappear when you go down to these lower levels of thoughts or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just stays there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing what happens to it, it gets ignored.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right order gets ignored and that's why you jump into assuming the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's possible for it not to be, because it is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's implicit in the mood, it's implicit in the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's always there, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the closest thing to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you understood that it can't not be there, then you wouldn't forget that it was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible to forget it is there, because forgetfulness is within that thing having to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's determined by being alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I say something?
[SPEAKER_00]: I used to think...
[SPEAKER_00]: I found it helpful to think of the mind as being like the light in the room.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm looking at you now and I can't see the light.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it certainly resembles the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something I can see and yet I know there's light.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't attend to the light.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only think things that were revealed by the light.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I know that there's light.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have any doubt about whether there's light in the room.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have to think about it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'd have to think about it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's... yeah, that's the... that implication that I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is implicit in the thoughts, in as much as the conscious body is implicit within the mind, within the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, can you even conceive looking, even perceiving the light, if you have no eyes and no body?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And no... and you're not alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that kind of leads to, then, to the final point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through your thoughts, you discern your mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop regarding the second.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see there's more primordial, simultaneously enduring, the fundamental container of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, you discern further necessary basis for your thoughts, for your mind, which is the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Body with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has arose.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was born, given.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're fully within it, fully subjected to its nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't that a thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but it's a thought that's made possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: By what?
[SPEAKER_00]: By the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but, see, the conscious body is a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you experience the conscious body
[SPEAKER_01]: In any other manner than having a thought of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you experience anything without that thing being also a thought there?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being, without that thing being fundamentally, primarily, a dhamma, a container, a thing, a thought, yeah, a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the difference then?
[SPEAKER_01]: From the starting point of Bhuttujana's thoughts, and then the point after you understand the relationship between the nature of the mind, the nature of the conscious body, and then you realize, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: What has changed?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess, seeing the difference between the thought and... And the thought, and the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, those thoughts, those thoughts resist you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're, you know, you find them there, you're subjected to those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're sort of... that's their externality, sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They... there's something beyond me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is another thought, but when... like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a notion of beyond me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's... it's not really beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's, let's, like, again, restart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have a... you have thoughts of agitation, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of the agitation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you recognize the unpleasant mood of that agitation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you stop, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Disordering it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop regarding the mood as a product of your thoughts, but you see that movements of your thoughts are within the container of the mood, which is why they move, which is why they shuffle and try to get... shake off the mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: That already frees you from the pressure of the thoughts, by discerning the right order of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thought of the mood is a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thought of the agitation within the mood that you want to get rid of is another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the difference is just wanting to get rid of it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting to get rid... And why do you want to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the necessary condition for wanting to get... What is the necessary condition for craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: Painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But something in regard to the painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the necessary condition?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, you can remove the craving and still have painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is it that you cannot have, if you remove the craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the assumption of the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not be trying to get rid of it, unless you assume that you can get rid of it by getting rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the movements you engage in are rooted in the assumption that you can... that moving can get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By understanding the order, by seeing the order in the right way, that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your whole mood changes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mood, your whole kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're out of the mood, you're beyond it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... You're truly beyond it, because you're not affected by it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no need...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's completely pointless.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, if you say, theoretically, yes, it's just thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is just thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a sense that, yeah, determined by the physical conscious body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, within the thoughts, there is the right order of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the right nature and there is the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the sole difference between a Bhutujana and an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean, like, oh, you go, you get to understand your mood on account of the thoughts, then you get to understand the necessary basis for both mood and the thoughts that move within the mood, is this conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you abandon that for understanding the nature of it, which is, yeah, you were subjected to, you were given, you have no say, it's on the level of the elements, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, oh, so I'm back onto the thoughts, as I always was.
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't have left it even if I wanted to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You couldn't have been outside of your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, for an arahant, in what's thought, there is only things that have been thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the scene, there's just a scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the thought, there is just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the herd, there's just a herd.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it can't be anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, see, in the scene, there is just a scene, means, in the scene, there is no more wrong order of the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the thought, there is no more wrong order of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, in the scene, there is just scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing else there.
[SPEAKER_01]: For Puttujāna, there is the whole world of difference there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world that's not outside of the scene, or result of the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the world that's the result of the wrong order of the scene, or the thought, or any other sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, getting the order right changes the significance of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, getting the order right, basically, what it means, prevents the gratuitous maintenance of the sense of ownership, the sense of self, the sense of conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I mean is, like, everyone can say, oh, I know what a thought is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you get the right order, then, when you say thought... Well, there are certain...
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say thought, you're talking about what the Buddha meant when he said thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a... that's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's... that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when people say, like, they would read the sutta, and then, oh, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, you understand it on some level, but then you have to see, understanding this, what does that result in?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the symptoms of having understand... having... having this understood?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, symptom is you're unable to... means you're unable to suffer, means you have destroyed birth, aging, death, sickness, anything that you're subjected to cannot possibly disturb any, like, completely effortless indifference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Equanimity is not something you must latch on to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the result of your understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're utterly unshakable as a result of your understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do you still think you understood the thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's always the main problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not really like
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have the right thoughts".
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like thinking that you have understood that which you haven't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that degree, you won't make effort to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you read the sutta, it makes sense, and you think you understood consciousness, you think you understood the mind, you think you understood the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... you just need to tidy it up a bit more.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you understood any of those, for what it is, if you understood what thought within a thought is, in thought there is just a thought, you would be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, on the other hand, well, no, I'm not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, I can't take for granted my understanding of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have an understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which gives me direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I could, well, because it makes sense to me, I can think that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, actually, it makes sense to me, but it's not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean, like, you, like, a person interested in practice should be very careful about
[SPEAKER_01]: Falling into this theoretical statement, so to speak, that then they deem are true and applicable to them as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha said in the scene, there is just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so in the scene, there is just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's only true for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you're not an arahant,
[SPEAKER_01]: For you, there is much more in the scene than just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, if you make the effort and get rid of the more, undo the more, understand the more, which is understand the wrong order and thus rectify it, then yes, in the scene, there has always been just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not true to say it when you...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's literally saying like, oh, I have...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have, I don't know, some...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a flu, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: And...
[SPEAKER_01]: The cure for this sickness is such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm still sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, are you free from your sickness on account of knowing that cure?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it's not a cure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you don't know enough of it or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, the point is to be free from sickness, not to have a theoretical knowledge of the cure that then you kind of infer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this applies to me because it applies to everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a universal truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you're still sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is a universal truth that in the seen there's just the seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: There can't be anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why when people jump, like, you know, when the Buddha talks about the element of nibbāna, it's there, present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then people develop the view, oh, so we are already in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because element of nibbāna, as in nibbāna, is always present in every one experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if you're enlightened or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means we are already all in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it means we are all already healthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you say that while you're still very much sick, and subjected to sickness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I said, theoretically, it's true, but it's completely wrong for you, because you are still sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will remain in the element of nibbāna, but you will not develop the nibbāna, because you... for as long as you remain sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you realize, so, what is nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: The knowing that nibbāna is the element, as in possibility, for everyone of us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that the same to say as, oh, no, you've made the effort and attained a nibbāna as a result of it, free from suffering, free from conceivings?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's the whole world of difference there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, element possibility of nibbāna is there, but it doesn't mean that you have fully developed the actual nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's you intentionally trying to obscure the difference between possible nibbāna, which is present, and the actual nibbāna, which is the possible nibbāna that has been developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're free from symptoms on account of not having developed a nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, nibbāna is part of everyone's experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what we refer to the element of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, yes, if you do things rightly, you can actualize that possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, it's not like... it's not like something you create, but it's something you discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's... that's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just pointing out that... Well, like, you know, those suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: I spoke about it recently.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've done the whole essay on it, the luminous mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the mind is radiant, luminous, not inhibited by anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's these gratuitous defilements that inhibit it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, defilements cannot really inhibit the luminosity of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's true for an arahant and for somebody who is free from the defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, in hindsight, you can know, as I said, in hindsight, when you arrive, that, oh, so this is a thought, but now the thought that has uprooted the whole wrong order, and then you realize,
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's still a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could have not been anything else from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can only say that once you abandon the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only say that the mind was truly always luminous and radiant and uninhibited once you have abandoned the defilement of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only reason you can abandon the defilement of it is because they can't truly defile the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's hard for people to recognize, well, theoretically this is true, but practically my situation starts from the opposite end.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for Putujana, he has to... he starts with defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not true for him to say that mind is pure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, he'll fall into a view that my mind is pure regardless of my sickness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha, when, depending on the context and who he was talking to, he would say, like, if he talks to Putujana about the five aggregates or about the mind, he would then say, for an arahant, five aggregates have ceased.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the aggregates are gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, because, yes, Putujana's aggregates, which are the aggregates of the wrong order, the only aggregates he can know of, are completely gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: They do not exist as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you would...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not always productive to address things on this theoretical level, because then, as I said, somebody who is not free from illness would understand these things in theory and then think, okay, so that's what the understanding of that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, if you truly understood it, you would be free from the illness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, so how does then the mind get polluted, if mind cannot be polluted?
[SPEAKER_01]: That is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That mistake of thinking the pollution, thinking the mind is like this, when it can't be like that, is beginningless, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no first point, before which avijja wasn't, and then avijja becomes the manifest, that you can discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, Puthujjana and his view was always as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why once you undo it and you recognize the mind could have not...
[SPEAKER_01]: It made no difference to the mind or the aggregates, your craving and your upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could not have made a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you understand that, it's irreversible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The order was always like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The order was always right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how you take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for you, starting point was the assumption of your wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why upādāna is responsible for maintenance of the being, of the reality that you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, and why, like, sort of knowledge of these phenomena that the Buddha is talking about, is really just sort of allowing them to reveal... Yeah, so you remove the assumption of the reality that you know, you realize reality has stayed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that was always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts have always been the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the scene, they have always been just a scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it was the whole world of assumption that I had on top of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irreversible, once you undo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you remove the gratuitous, as the Buddha said, literally, that agantukha was the word, part of it, means like superimposed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means it cannot really become part of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Adventitious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Adventitious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you remove those gratuitous defilements, the gratuitous there could not have been there, should not have been there, not knowing that you were placing them there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove it, they cannot come back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot return, because there is no room for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha meant by upādāna is not in the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not part of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be part of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means five aggregates don't even know about your upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep putting it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're completely unaware of your upādāna, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can't put it there, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, but, well...
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, desire and lust means upādāna is there in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because you put it... what I mean is, because you put it there, it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, that's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only thing you know, is that this is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to acknowledge it first, that that's a starting point, and not start practice from this theoretical aspect of aggregates are already free, we are already in nibbāna, mind is already pure, I just need to scratch through the conventional reality until I discover
[SPEAKER_01]: Ultimate is only in response to conventional.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ultimate is determined by the conventional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Conventional is determined by the ultimate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you remain ignorant of the nature of reality of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if it's ultimate or conventional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reality is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the difference is not in reality and the characteristics of reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: The difference is in the wrong order you assume in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not in the conventional reality, nor the ultimate reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, that completely gratuitous division is wrong, utterly wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the way I would say, even for the targeter.
[SPEAKER_01]: As far as the language goes, as far as the conventions and designations go, the Taoist has understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hasn't blamed it for his ignorance and then replaced it with the greater ultimate reality by removing the veil of maya or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It stays.
[SPEAKER_00]: He still uses words, he still designates.
[SPEAKER_01]: What has changed is the wrong assumption, the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: What comes first, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why it's so hard to see is because in thought, there is only a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But which one of those thought-thought you put first?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, well, whichever it is, it must be wrong, because you're not an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, try and do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go against the stream.
[SPEAKER_00]: Against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Against the grain, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's like, oh, consciousness is this, mind is this, thoughts are that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're all thoughts for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you know consciousness if it's not a thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you know your mind, your mood, unless you're thinking it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you know your thoughts unless they're being thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the order of those things?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only arrive at these things in... with understanding, is if you arrive at them through the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, in the previous talk, or one of the previous talks we've done, was the... you can only know I, sights and consciousness...
[SPEAKER_00]: Through the contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, pressure doesn't disappear when you think about consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eyes don't disappear... pressure doesn't disappear when you think about the eyes or objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your pressure is where the knowledge is of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just emphasizing different aspects within the whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, like, oh, now I'm thinking about consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you're thinking about your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're thinking about your thoughts within a mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're thinking about the thoughts within a mood about consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always... you're always thinking the same things, which is thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just ceasing to assume the, you know, the external point of view, or any form of wrong order, any manifestation of the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what comes first is the thought within a thought of mood, within a thought of the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you think, oh, this is just a thought of consciousness, and then there is consciousness
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thought that you gave a gratuitous property of being external, real, as opposed to this unreal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, that's another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: That notion of externality as opposed to internality is another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trapped.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trapped.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you think that your escape from it is removing the thought, you'll remain trapped forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically just stop assuming the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will remove the symptoms of any illness and disease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, in another way of saying that, is that whatever can be thought, whatever can be experienced, is impermanent, depends on something that I have no control over.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you experience anything without the conscious body being there?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have not seen it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you get to pick and choose your consciousness?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you have to pick and choose your body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any difference that you can make to the body is within the body that's given to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's only a secondary difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not really a difference of the fundamental nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only borrow the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can use it while it's borrowed, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But at no point it becomes yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason you can borrow it is because it's always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not forgetting that context, for example, that whatever you do, whatever you think, whatever you feel, whatever you...
[SPEAKER_01]: You've done whatever you're planning to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibly doing, if you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within the container of the body being there, given to you, conscious body being there, given to you, and you're not saying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And learn how to allow that image, so to speak, to endure peripherally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without you trying to overly attend it and get out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't get out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only...
[SPEAKER_00]: Forget it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only basically drain away your sense of self within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: By removing any notion of the external ownership, you will remove the basis for maintenance of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I feel like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel superior.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel inferior.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel equal.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is possible only because there is this still conscious body there and I'm not saying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, my own sense of self, I undermine by realizing that I cannot own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it ceases to be myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, discerning the context and maintaining the discernment of that context, not attending to the context, because you'll be doing that with yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not a context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start attending it, it ceases to be the context.